Guide to the Records of the A/P/A Voices A COVID-19 Public Memory Project TAM.837
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Chiu, Yucan, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_16
  Materials include a transcript and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Sarah Lin on July 22, 2020. In his interview, Yucan Chiu discusses grief, numbness, and disorientation at the start of the pandemic – especially as someone whose work relies on face-to-face interaction. Chiu also discusses the disproportionate impact of COVID-19 on the Black and Brown communities within the community he serves; how the pandemic and its impact raised theological questions and reflections; and the need for local human touch in the midst of COVID-19 and the disconnection it brought. Chiu talks about how he helped put together COVID-19 relief efforts with other leaders in New Brunswick, NJ and the need for caring leadership in times of crisis. Chiu also discusses the importance of faith partnerships; multifaith work and coordination in a pandemic setting; the resilience of the human spirit in the face of crisis; and the need for systemic transformation in the seasons ahead.
  Reverend Dr. Yucan Chiu, D.Min. was born in Chicago to parents of Chinese descent. Chiu came to understand and experience Jesus in his teenage years while in California, and began to help create and lead faith communities in his early 20s. He holds bachelor degrees in Sociology and Biology from the University of California, San Diego; and graduate degrees in Theology, Urban Studies, and Missiology (M.Div, Talbot School of Theology, D.Min. Bakke Graduate University). Chiu has been married for 20 years to Dr. Yen-Yen Chiu, Ed.D. (an educator in the public schools) and has two teenage daughters. Chiu serves as a chaplain at Rutgers University, a trainer for City to City, and the Director of the Ethnos Network.
- Chow, Yvonne, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_17
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Linda Kuo on August 30, 2021. In her interview, Yvonne Chow discusses how COVID-19 has impacted her ability to create choreography; the virtual shift for her dance company; and the challenge to stay connected with and be of service for the community when in-person events were limited. Chow also talks about Dance Mart, the free grocery, health services, and resources program offered by H+; and setting up a grocery delivery program for dancers during the pandemic.
  Chow addresses racial tensions and reckonings with the racial divide and disconnection in the Hip Hop community during attacks against Asian Americans. She shares opportunities for connecting more deeply with Asian American women, selfcare, building solidarity, and her upcoming projects -- all as responses to anti-Asian racism during the pandemic. Chow further talks about her work with H+ and House of Chow; building communities; and forging relationships toward racial solidarity and dancer economic sustainability.
  Yvonne Chow is a first-generation Chinese American woman from the Bay Area in California. As of 2021, she has been living in New York City for over a decade and is the Education Director for H+/ Hip Hop Dance Conservatory. She's also the founder of House of Chow, the Asian (American) division of H+.
- Choy, Catherine Ceniza, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_18
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Rosario Joaquin on December 7, 2020. During the interview, Catherine Ceniza Choy begins by sharing a personal story about traveling in Europe during the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic and how she began to witness anti-Asian sentiment stem from fear of the virus. Upon returning to her home in California, Choy talks about the emotional toll of her trip to Europe; making the decision to lend her voice to the media as a historian and scholar in order to counter misinformation; and attempts to portray Asian-Americans in a more human light. She highlights many projects from the Filipino American community and examples of community care, including the Philippine Nurses Association of America's (PNAA) Heal Our Nurses campaign; Kanlungan; the Philippine Health Initiative for Research, Service, and Training (PHIRST); and This Filipino American Life.
  Catherine Ceniza Choy is the Professor of Ethnic Studies and an Associate Dean of the College of Letters & Science's Division of Undergraduate Studies at the University of California, Berkeley. She is the author of several books on Asian American history, Filipino American studies, race, gender, and migration, including Empire of Care: Nursing and Migration in Filipino American History (2003). At the time of this interview, Choy had completed 30 interviews since February 2020 and continued to bring light to the critical role Filipino American nurses play in the U.S. healthcare system.
- Dancers Unlimited, 2019, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_19
  Dancers Unlimited (DU) is a bi-coastal 501(c)3 nonprofit company based in New York City and Hawai'i. DU creates authentic MoveMeant narratives for community advancement through creative collaboration, community engagement, and social justice work. Established in 2009, the company has presented work in festivals and showings in Hawai'i, New York City, and Asia.
  This material includes two videos: "I'mMigration / Ku Kia'i Mauna" and "AAPI Community Discussion."
  I'mMigration/Ku Kia'i Mauna was performed on September 10, 2019. The work explores the kuleana, or responsibility, of members of the Hawaiian community to decolonize by connecting with their heritage and building allyship to support Indigenous rights. This relates to the proposed controversial development of the Thirty Meter Telescope at Mauna Kea, which continued during the pandemic. This dance was performed by Dancers Unlimited NYC and Hawai'i dancers; was performed at the Arts at Mark's Garage in Honolulu, HI; and was part of the Small Plates Dance Festival. The videographer was Mark Feijão Millian.
  The AAPI Community Discussion was recorded on May 30, 2021. It was hosted by Dancers Unlimited, Peridance, and the Mark Morris Dance Center for an Asian American Pacific Islander (AAPI) Solidarity fundraiser and community discussion. The discussion portion was moderated by Jessica Chen, the Director of JChen Project, and Yaya Yuan, the Director of Education and Mentoring Programs at APEX For Youth.
- Dang, Cathy, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_20
  Materials include a transcript and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Vivian Truong on July 14, 2020. In the interview, Cathy Dang discusses her personal experiences with pregnancy during the first several months of the pandemic. She also discusses how the government response to COVID-19 in Vietnam, where her parents live, was different from the response in the U.S.; her sister's experience losing their job in Hawai'i and sewing masks for healthcare workers; and the potential connections between unemployed people and essential workers.
  Dang also discusses her participation in the Black Lives Matter (BLM) protests after the police killing of George Floyd in Minneapolis. She reflects on how the pandemic and uprisings have affected Crown Heights, NY, where she was living at the time of this interview. As the daughter of a small business owner, she offers her analysis on Asian immigrant responses to the uprisings and the movement to defund the police in New York City. Finally, Dang shares her hopes and concerns for the movement and her own family; and what she wants her future child to understand about the moment that they are being born into.
  Cathy Dang grew up in New York City and Los Angeles, CA. She has been a community and labor organizer for over fifteen years. She was the former director of CAAAV: Organizing Asian Communities. She is a Soros Equality Fellow and an advisor with the Center for Empowered Politics.
- Desis Rising Up & Moving (DRUM), circa 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_21
  Materials include a "Building Power & Safety Through Solidarity" flyer.
- Diente, Xenia, 2021
  - Digital Files, TW_TAM_837_ER_22
    Materials include video files from an oral history interview conducted by Tomie Arai on January 18, 2021. A flyer titled "Bayanihan Response to COVID-19 in the Northeast" is also included. In this interview, Xenia Diente shares her personal experience traveling in the Philippines when COVID-19 first started in March and her family's immigration history from the Philippines. Diente provides historical background around the labor exportation policies that resulted in large numbers of Filipino nurses immigrating to the U.S. -- her mother is a retired nurse and her entire family are health care workers impacted by the pandemic.
    Diente talks about her new interest in Philippine history as a result of her community-based art practice. As a 2020 fellow with the Laundromat Project, Diente and her partner, Jaclyn, initially proposed a series of public art activations celebrating the Filipino diaspora in Queens, but quickly pivoted to a mutual aid project during the pandemic that sought to support the brick and mortar businesses of Little Manila. Diente discusses the geography of Queens; and talks in depth about the different languages and social make up of the Filipino community in Queens. The last half of the interview is spent talking about the Meal to Heal project, her participation in a mural created for frontline workers around the concept of 'Mabuhay' (a Filipino expression that means 'may you live'), and community efforts to rename a stretch of Roosevelt Avenue, 'Little Manila Street'.
    The video files of this oral history interview can be accessed in the NYU Special Collections reading room or remotely.
    Xenia Diente is a Filipina and a Queens-based public art professional who works for the New York City Department of Design and Construction (DDC). Diente sits on the board of the Filipino American National History Society-Metro NY Chapter. She was a Laundromat Project Create Change Fellow when she and her partner Jaclyn Reyes developed "The Meal to Heal Initiative" in April 2020, in response to the COVID-19 crisis in New York City. Meal to Heal was a mutual aid project that paired Filipino restaurants in Queens with local hospitals and nursing homes, providing free meals to frontline health care workers. This initiative was created for the Laundromat Project, by Little Manila Queens Bayanihan Arts, in partnership with the National Alliance for Filipino Concerns USA North East Chapter and the Filipino American National Historical Society Metro NY Chapter.
- Eda, Haruki, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_23
  Materials include a transcript and audio files from an oral history interview conducted by Mi Hyun Yoon on March 15, 2021. In his interview, Haruki Eda speaks about his engagement with Nodutdol and Eclipse Rising; and how his experiences as an organizer have changed due to the pandemic. In particular, Eda took the pandemic as an opportunity to shift his thinking and refocus on what he actually wants to do with his life – he shifted his career aspirations from academia to urban forestry. Eda also talks about his family in Japan and teaching an Asian American studies class at a time when anti-Asian hatred and racism have increased.
  The transcript and audio files of this oral history interview can be accessed in the NYU Special Collections reading room or remotely.
  Haruki Eda is a community organizer involved with NoDutDol for Korean Community Development and Eclipse Rising, both of which are organizations for Zainichi Koreans, or postcolonial exiles of Korean descent in Japan. Eda identifies as Zainichi Korean and as of 2021, he was a PhD candidate in sociology at Rutgers University.
- Emma, 2021; TW_TAM_837_ER_24
  Materials include a transcript and audio files from an oral history interview conducted by Emma Callahan on September 13, 2021. In her interview, Emma talks about her experiences protesting during the Black Lives Matter (BLM) movement throughout the summer of 2020. She mentions the importance of getting involved and why she felt her participation was necessary. Emma also discusses a collective change in attitudes towards the protests by the end of the summer, specifically how as people's lives changed, in person protests were deprioritized. Emma reflects and questions the ways in which the George Floyd protests could have lasting impact on people's lives.
  Emma addresses her own complicated feelings during the Stop Asian Hate movement in early 2021 and discusses finding community in a group of neighborhood and childhood friends who were primarily Asian women. At the same time, Emma expresses feeling a strange need to make a resounding statement, especially on social media, about the Stop Asian Hate movement. She was unsure of how to take ownership of Stop Asian American and Pacific Island (AAPI) Hate when an increase in anti-Asian violence was not something she had personally experienced. Emma discusses how her own identity as an Asian-American has evolved and changed over the past year, especially with the realization that she is seen as an Asian woman by her white peers.
  Emma is a mixed-race Korean-American musician and artist from the Lower East Side of New York City.
- Fincher, Beverly Hong, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_25
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Diane Wong on December 11, 2020. A photograph of Beverly Hong Fincher is also included. The interview starts with Fincher discussing her career as a linguist and her first academic position; and her research, teaching, and lecturing on Chinese language and discourse analysis. Fincher goes on to discuss the intellectual life and community she was a part of in Washington D.C., where she lived before the pandemic, and feeling lonely and disconnected since moving back to New York City over the summer.
  Throughout the interview, Fincher shares fond memories of visiting different places to give lectures. She recalls visiting Meridian House to give a talk and was gifted a silk jacket covered with a famous Chinese poetry, which she recited aloud. She also recalls a chance encounter with an ambassador on her way back from China, choosing to sit next to him on the shuttle bus to the airport, while advocating for anti-smoking laws to be passed in China. To her surprise, a few weeks later, she saw there was a nationwide law passed on smoking. She claims this moment to be one of her proudest accomplishments because it saved lives. Towards the end of the interview, Fincher discusses how difficult life has been for her in quarantine and how her mental health has suffered. Although she has found joy from visiting Manhattan Chinatown, her visits are infrequent.
  Beverly Hong Fincher is a linguist and academic.
- Fu, Lisa, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_26
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Preeti Sharma on July 29, 2020. The bulk of the interview focuses on the pandemic's impact on the predominantly Vietnamese staffed and owned nail salon sector in California, especially in terms of statewide closing and reopening policies. The interview opens with Lisa Fu's initial experiences in the pandemic, detailing her personal schedule and quarantine routine as a mother of two children with immunosuppressed family members at home. Fu also discusses details about how the first shut down impacted workers and independent contractors, including access barriers to unemployment insurance and loans for business owners.
  Fu shares the Healthy Nail Salon Collaborative's decision to raise emergency aid and create a Nail Salon Community Care Fund. She also highlights the Collaborative's response to the Governor's false claim that the first wave of COVID-19 in California originated from nail salons. Fu considers the challenges of what reopening nail salons in California could look like, particularly given the different speeds of reopening across the country, across the state, and the damage of the Governor's false claim; and the types of guidelines and advocacy the Collaborative could offer these businesses. Fu discusses how the Collaborative acted in solidarity with the Black Lives Matter (BLM) protests. She closes the interview considering aspects of anti-Asian racism in salons and the ongoing toxic chemicals and respiratory issues in salons that have been exacerbated by COVID-19.
  Lisa Fu was born and raised in Los Angeles, CA. She received her Master of Public Health in 2003 and was previously the National Organizing Director for the National Asian Pacific American Women's Forum. As of 2020, she lives in Los Angeles and is the Executive Director of the California Healthy Nail Salon Collaborative.
- Gao, Cynthia "Cindy", 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_27
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Tomie Arai on September 15, 2020. In her interview, Cynthia Gao talks extensively about the neighborhood of Flatbush in Brooklyn, which is a largely Caribbean community with a sizable population of healthcare workers. She describes her experiences providing mutual aid through Equality for Flatbush and delivering food during the pandemic. Gao reflects on the ways the lock-down impacted her and covers a number of topics from policing and community safety; her role in the Black Lives Matter (BLM) protests; anti-Asian racism; and the challenges of organizing radical mutual aid efforts, which she envisions can be a way to build consciousness and community power.
  Cynthia Gao is Chinese American and as of 2020, a PhD student in the Department of Social and Cultural Analysis at New York University. She is researching the influence of Revolutionary Asia on Communist and radical movements in the United States. Cynthia was a volunteer with A/P/A Voices: A COVID 19 Public Memory Project during the summer of 2020, as part of her work with the Center for Global Asia. Until recently, Cindy was a member of Equality for Flatbush, a Black/person of color led grassroots organization in Brooklyn that fights for affordable housing and mobilizes against gentrification and displacement in Flatbush, East Flatbush, and Brooklyn-wide.
- Garcia-Dia, Mary Joy, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_28
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Rosario Joaquin on December 4, 2020. During the interview, Mary Joy Garcia-Dia discusses the successes and challenges she encountered in organizing the Philippine Nurses Association of America's (PNAA) response to COVID-19, including her promotion to President in June 2020 as the virus quickly showed a disproportionate impact on her local, national, and international community of Filipino nurses. Garcia-Dia emphasizes the value of resilience, the topic of her doctoral research, and the theme of her PNAA presidency. She discusses various PNAA initiatives, including the organization's COVID-19 Task Force, the Heal Our Nurses campaign, and their resilience training program. Garcia-Dia also shares personal reflections of how the COVID-19 pandemic compares to her experiences working as a bedside nurse during the 1990s HIV crisis. Finally, Garcia-Dia discusses the importance of cross-cultural solidarity and disaggregated health data as we imagine a post-COVID-19 world and seek to not repeat the tragedies of this virus.
  Mary Joy Garcia-Dia is the Program Director of Nursing Informatics at NewYork-Presbyterian Hospital. She is the former President-Elect and President of the Philippine Nurses Association of America, Inc. (PNAA), one of the oldest and largest non-profit professional nursing organizations in the country.
- Gina, 2021
  - Digital Files, TW_TAM_837_ER_29
    Materials include video files from an oral history interview conducted by Mi Hyun Yoon on March 12, 2021. Photographs of Gina and her family are also included. The interview begins with Gina discussing the rise of Asian hate crimes. She mentions that even before the pandemic, in January and February of 2020, people in her hometown area of Dallas Fort Worth, TX would avoid her or give her strange looks as an Asian-presenting woman.
    On a personal level, the pandemic has changed many aspects of Gina's personal life. She realized many of her friends were harboring their own prejudices and would not take radical action to combat racism in their everyday lives. Gina became more involved in radical social justice organizing and discourse online through Twitter and Reddit. She explains that online platforms have helped her connect with communities across the world and stay informed about breaking news. In addition to social media, Gina has participated in various radical-left podcasts over the pandemic including Mango Press or Escape from Plan A.
    Gina explains how the racially charged violence of the pandemic angered and radicalized her. It also revealed her complicated feelings about the narrative of Asian-Americans in anti-Black racism. As the daughter of a Korean store owner, Gina expresses discomfort about how Asians are often excluded or othered in communities of color or constantly othered as non-American. Gina feels incidents like the L.A. Riots often flatten and simplify narratives that place blame on Asian communities. Gina also expresses frustration that small businesses of working-class store owners, like her mother, were targeted during the Black Lives Matter protests in 2020. Gina questions a desire to go back to a "normal" post-pandemic world and questions what normal means in a post-pandemic world.
    Gina is a multi-racial Asian-American woman living and working in the southern United States. Born in South Korea on a military base, she grew up in Southern Texas and is of a Tejana and Korean descent. As of 2020, Gina works for a health insurance company.
- Hoa, Vincent, 2020; TW_TAM_837_ER_30
  Materials include a transcript, audio files, and video files from an oral history interview conducted by Cynthia Gao on June 18, 2020. The first part of the interview concerns Vincent Hoa's experience as a city gardener whose position was declared "essential" during the first lockdown of the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020. He describes the confusion and lack of consistent direction given by his immediate supervisors, union representatives, and the city before and after the lockdown. According to Hoa, safety precautions varied and were inconsistent and there was a lack of personal protective equipment (PPE) available for workers.
  Hoa discusses contracting COVID-19, his belief he contracted the virus through working, and the process of accessing a test in the early months of the pandemic. Attitudes towards COVID-19 among parks workers is discussed, as are conspiracy theories, beliefs about its origins in China, and questions about why parks workers were considered essential. Hoa describes some of the emotional and psychological impacts of working through the pandemic and getting sick; the kinds of work he performed; and the kinds of safety precautions he took.